In this video we'll talk about
このビデオでは、
an approach to building a
協調フィルタリングと呼ばれる
recommender system that's called collaborative filtering.
リコメンダーシステム構築のアプローチを議論する。
The algorithm that we're talking
これから議論するアルゴリズムは
about has a very interesting
とても興味深い性質を
property that it does
持っていて、それは
what is called feature learning and
フィーチャーラーニングと呼ばれている。
by that I mean that this
それの意味する所は、
will be an algorithm that can
これはアルゴリズムが、
start to learn for itself what features to use.
なんのフィーチャーを使うかを自分自身で学習しはじめる事を意味する。
Here was the data set that
こんなデータセットが
we had and we had
あるとしよう。
assumed that for each movie,
そして各映画ごとに、
someone had come and told
誰かがやってきてその映画が
us how romantic that
どのくらいロマンティックか、
movie was and how much action there was in that movie.
どれだけのアクションが入っているかを教えてくれるとしよう。
But as you can imagine it
でも、想像出来るように、
can be very difficult and time
実際に誰かが
consuming and expensive to actually try
個々の映画を見ていって、
to get someone to, you know,
それらがどれくらいロマンティックか、
watch each movie and tell
どれだけのアクションが詰め込まれているかを
you how romantic each movie and
いちいち教えてもらうのは
how action packed is each
とても難しく、とても時間がかかり、とても高く付く場合がありうる。
movie, and often you'll
しかもしばしば、フィーチャーは
want even more features than just these two.
たった2つよりもずっと多く必要となる。
So where do you get these features from?
ではこれらのフィーチャーはどこから得たらいいか？
So let's change the problem
そこでちょっと問題を変更して
a bit and suppose that
これらのフィーチャーを知らない
we have a data set where
データセットを
we do not know the values of these features.
持っていたとしよう。
So we're given the data set
つまり我らは、映画の集合と
of movies and of
それらをユーザーがどうレートしたのかのデータを
how the users rated them, but we
与えられたとする。
have no idea how romantic each
だが個々の映画がどのくらいロマンティックか
movie is and we have no
個々の映画にどのくらいアクションが詰まってるのかは
idea how action packed each
まったく分からないとする、
movie is so I've replaced all of these things with question marks.
つまりこれらをはてなマークで置き換えた。
But now let's make a slightly different assumption.
だがここで、ちょっとだけ別の仮定をおこう。
Let's say we've gone to each of our users, and each of our users has told has told us
ユーザー一人一人の所におもむく事が出来て、各ユーザーが我らに、
how much they like the
彼らがどれくらいロマンティックな映画が好きか、
romantic movies and how much
どれくらいアクションの映画が好きか、
they like action packed movies.
教えてくれるとしよう。
So Alice has associated a current of theta 1.
Aliceはシータ1に関連付けられているとしよう。
Bob theta 2.
Bobはシータ2に。
Carol theta 3.
Carolはシータ3に。
Dave theta 4.
Daveはシータ4に。
And let's say we also use this
そしてこれを使う事としよう、
and that Alice tells us
Aliceは我らに
that she really
彼女はロマンティック映画を
likes romantic movies and so
とても好きだ、と教えてくれて、
there's a five there which
だからそこには5を、
is the multiplier associated with X1 and lets
そこはx1の係数に対応する、
say that Alice tells us she
そしてまたAliceはアクション映画を
really doesn't like action movies and so there's a 0 there.
まったく好きでは無い、とも教えてくれた。だからそこは0とする。
And Bob tells us something similar
そしてBobも同じような事を言ったとする、
so we have theta 2 over here.
だからシータ2はこんな風になる。
Whereas Carol tells us that
一方Carolは、彼女は
she really likes action movies
アクション映画が大好きだと教えてくれたとする、
which is why there's a 5 there,
だからここが5となっている。
that's the multiplier associated with X2,
ここはx2の係数に対応する所だ。
and remember there's also
そしてまたx0も存在してて
X0 equals 1 and let's
それはイコール1なのも思い出そう。
say that Carol tells us
そしてCarolは我らに
she doesn't like romantic
ロマンティックな映画は嫌いだ、とも、
movies and so on, similarly for Dave.
教えてくれたとしよう。Daveも同様だ。
So let's assume that somehow
つまり、どうにかして我らが各ユーザーの元におもむき、
we can go to users and
各ユーザーjは我らに
each user J just tells
シータjの値を
us what is the value
教えてくれたと
of theta J for them.
想定してみよう。
And so basically specifies to us of how much they like different types of movies.
つまり、基本的には彼らが別々の種類の映画をどのくらい好きかを表明してくれるという事だ。
If we can get these parameters
もし我らはこれらのパラメータ、シータを
theta from our users then it
ユーザーから得る事が出来れば、
turns out that it becomes possible to
各映画のx1とx2の値が幾つかを
try to infer what are the
推測出来る、という事が
values of x1 and x2 for each movie.
判明する。
Let's look at an example.
例を見てみよう。
Let's look at movie 1.
映画1を見てみよう。
So that movie 1 has associated
映画1はフィーチャーベクトルx1に
with it a feature vector x1.
関連づけられているのだった。
And you know this movie is called Love at last but let's ignore that.
そしてこの映画がLove at lastと呼ばれていたのも知ってるだろうが、ここではそれは無視しよう。
Let's pretend we don't know what
この映画がなんなのか、知らないフリをしよう、
this movie is about, so let's ignore the title of this movie.
だからこの映画のタイトルを無視しよう。
All we know is that Alice loved this move.
Aliceがこの映画を好きだ、というのが我らの知っている全てだ。
Bob loved this movie.
Bobはこの映画が好きだ。
Carol and Dave hated this movie.
CarolとDaveはこの映画を嫌ってる。
So what can we infer?
ではそこから、何が推測出来るだろうか？
Well, we know from the
フィーチャーベクトルから我らは
feature vectors that Alice
AliceとBobはロマンティックな映画が
and Bob love romantic movies
好きだという事を知っている。
because they told us that there's a 5 here.
だって彼らはここは5だと告げてたのだから。
Whereas Carol and Dave,
他方、CarolとDaveは
we know that they hate
彼らはロマンティックな映画を
romantic movies and that
嫌ってる事を我らは知っている。
they love action movies. So
そして彼らはアクション映画を好んでいる。
because those are the parameter
つまりそれらがユーザー3と4、つまりCarolとDaveが
vectors that you know, uses 3 and 4, Carol and Dave, gave us.
我らにくれたパラメーターベクトルなので、
And so based on the fact
そして映画1はAliceとBobに
that movie 1 is loved
好まれていて、
by Alice and Bob and
CarolとDaveに嫌われているという事実に基づくと、
hated by Carol and Dave, we might
我らはこれがロマンティックな映画だと
reasonably conclude that this is probably a romantic movie,
合理的に結論出来る。
it is probably not much of an action movie.
それはたぶん、そんなにアクション映画では無かろう。
this example is a little
この例はちょっと
bit mathematically simplified but what
計算的に単純化してあるが、
we're really asking is what
我らが真に問うている事は
feature vector should X1 be
シータ1転置 x1が
so that theta 1 transpose
だいたい5となるような
x1 is approximately equal to 5,
x1とはなんだろう？という事だ。
that's Alice's rating, and
この5とはAliceのレーティング。
theta 2 transpose x1 is
シータ2の転置 x1も
also approximately equal to 5,
だいたいイコール5だ。
and theta 3 transpose x1 is
そしてシータ3転置 x1は
approximately equal to 0,
だいたい0に。
so this would be Carol's rating, and
これはCarolのレーティングだ。
theta 4 transpose X1
そしてシータ4転置 x1は
is approximately equal to 0.
だいたいイコール0。
And from this it looks
そしてこの事から
like, you know, X1 equals
x1はイコール、
one that's the intercept term, and
まず切片項の1に
then 1.0, 0.0, that makes sense
続いて1.0 0.0みたいになる。
given what we know of Alice,
それは既知のAlice、Bob、
Bob, Carol, and Dave's preferences
Carol、Daveの映画に関する
for movies and the way they rated this movie.
嗜好から、そして彼らがこの映画をどう評価するかの知識から、筋が通ってるように思う。
And so more generally, we can
より一般的には
go down this list and try
このリストを降りていって、
to figure out what might
これらの他の映画のフィーチャーも
be reasonable features for these other movies as well.
どんなだったらリーズナブルか見つけようと試みる事が出来る。
Let's formalize this problem of learning the features XI.
このxiを学習するという問題を定式化しよう。
Let's say that our
ユーザーが我らに
users have given us their preferences.
自分の嗜好を教えてくれるとする。
So let's say that our users have
つまり我らのユーザーが来てくれて、
come and, you know, told us
シータ1からシータnuまでの値を
these values for theta 1
教えてくれると
through theta of NU
しよう。
and we want to learn the
そして映画iに関する
feature vector XI for movie
フィーチャーベクトルxiを学習したい。
number I. What we can
だから我らがやる事は
do is therefore pose the following optimization problem.
以下のような最適化問題を解く事だ。
So we want to sum over
その為、映画iを
all the indices J for
レーティングしたユーザー全員にわたって
which we have a rating
インデックスjに関する
for movie I because
和を取りたい。
we're trying to learn the features
何故なら我らが学習したいのは
for movie I that is this feature vector XI.
映画iのフィーチャーだからで、それはフィーチャーベクトルxiだ。
So and then what we
だから、そこでやりたい事は
want to do is minimize this squared
この二乗誤差を最小化したい、
error, so we want to choose
つまりフィーチャーxiを
features XI, so that,
ユーザーjが映画iを
you know, the predictive value of
どうレーティングするかの予測値が
how user J rates movie
二乗誤差の意味で
I will be similar,
実際の値y ij、つまりユーザーjの映画iに対する
will be not too far in the
実際のレーティングの観測値に近い、
squared error sense of the actual
そんなに離れていないように、
value YIJ that we actually observe in
フィーチャーxiを
the rating of user j
選びたい。
on movie I. So, just to
ではまとめの為に、
summarize what this term does
この項がしている事は、
is it tries to choose features
フィーチャーxiを
XI so that for
以下の条件を満たすように選ぶ。
all the users J that
その条件とは、その映画をレーティングしている
have rated that movie, the
全てのユーザーjに対して、
algorithm also predicts a
アルゴリズムが予測するそのユーザーの
value for how that user would have rated that movie
その映画のレーティングが、実際の値とそんなに離れていないように
that is not too far, in
という条件だ。
the squared error sense, from the
離れていないとはユーザーが実際にその映画に対して行ったレーティングからの
actual value that the user had rated that movie.
二乗誤差の意味でだ。
So that's the squared error term.
これが二乗誤差の項だ。
As usual, we can
いつも通り、この種の
also add this sort of
正規化項を足して、
regularization term to prevent
フィーチャーが大きくなりすぎるのを
the features from becoming too big.
防止する事も出来る。
So this is how we
さて、以上が一つの特定の映画の
would learn the features
フィーチャーを
for one specific movie but
学習する方法だが、
what we want to do is
我らがやりたいのは、
learn all the features for all
全ての映画の全てのフィーチャーを
the movies and so what
学習する事だ。
I'm going to do is add this
だからやるべき事は、この追加の
extra summation here so
シグマをここに追加して、
I'm going to sum over all Nm
n m個の映画全てに渡って和を取る、
movies, N subscript m movies, and minimize
n下付き添字m 個の映画について、そしてこの
this objective on top
目的関数を最小化する、
that sums of all movies.
全ての映画についての和の。
And if you do that, you end up with the following optimization problem.
それを行うと、結局以下のような最適化の問題となる。
And if you minimize
これを最小化すると、
this, you have hopefully a
全ての映画についての、
reasonable set of features for all of your movies.
リーズナブルなフィーチャーの集合が得られる事が期待出来る。
So putting everything together, what
全てをあわせると、
we, the algorithm we talked
我らが前のビデオで議論してきた
about in the previous video and
アルゴリズムと、
the algorithm that we just talked about in this video.
このビデオで今議論してきたアルゴリズムは
In the previous video, what we
前のビデオで見てきたのは
showed was that you know,
えーと、
if you have a set of
映画のレーティングの集合が
movie ratings, so if you
あったとすると、
have the data the rij's and
つまりデータr ijとy ij、
then you have the yij's that will be the movie ratings.
それは映画のレーティングだが、それがあったとすると、
Then given features for your
別々の映画に対してのフィーチャーが所与であれば、
different movies we can learn these parameters theta.
これらのパラメータ、シータが学習出来る、という事だった。
So if you knew the features,
つまり、もしフィーチャーを知ってたら、
you can learn the parameters
別々のユーザーのパラメータ、シータを
theta for your different users.
学習する事が出来る。
And what we showed earlier in
そしてこのビデオの前半で
this video is that if
見てきたように、
your users are willing to
もしユーザーがあなたに
give you parameters, then you
喜んでパラメータを提供してくれれば、
can estimate features for the different movies.
別々の映画のフィーチャーを推計する事が出来る。
So this is kind of a chicken and egg problem.
つまりこれは、鶏と卵の問題だ。
Which comes first?
どっちが先に来る？
You know, do we want if we can get the thetas, we can know the Xs.
シータが得られれば、xを知る事が出来る。
If we have the Xs, we can learn the thetas.
xが分かっていれば、シータを学習出来る。
And what you can
そこでとりうる手段としては、
do is, and then
そしてこれは実際に
this actually works, what you
うまく行くのだが、それは、
can do is in fact randomly
出来る事は、実際にランダムに
guess some value of the thetas.
シータの何らかの値を推測してしまう、という事だ。
Now based on your initial random
この最初のランダムなシータの
guess for the thetas, you can
推測に基づいて、
then go ahead and use
前進する事が出来て、
the procedure that we just talked
別々の映画のフィーチャーを学習する為に
about in order to
ここまで話してきた手順が
learn features for your different movies.
使える事になる。
Now given some initial set
今、何らかのフィーチャーの初期の値が
of features for your movies you
映画に対して与えられたとき、
can then use this first
この前回のビデオで話した
method that we talked about
最初の手法を用いて
in the previous video to try to get
パラメータシータの推計を
an even better estimate for your parameters theta.
改善する事が出来る。
Now that you have a better setting of the parameters theta for your users,
いまやユーザーのシータの改善された値を得たので、
we can use that to maybe
それを用いてさらにフィーチャーを
even get a better set of
改善した物が得られるかもしれない、
features and so on.
などなど。
We can sort of keep
ある種の繰り返しを
iterating, going back and forth
続ける事で、行ったり来たりする事で、
and optimizing theta, x theta,
シータ、x、シータ、x、シータ、xと
x theta, nd this
最適化をしていく事が出来る。
actually works and if you
これは実際に機能する。
do this, this will actually
これを行うと、これは実際に
cause your album to converge
映画のフィーチャーと
to a reasonable set of
ユーザーごとに異なったパラメータの
features for you movies and a
リーズナブルな組に
reasonable set of parameters for your different users.
収束する。
So this is a basic collaborative filtering algorithm.
以上が基本的な協調的フィルタリングのアルゴリズムだ。
This isn't actually the final
これは実際に使う、最終的なアルゴリズムでは
algorithm that we're going to use. In the next
無い。次のビデオで、
video we are going to be able to improve
このアルゴリズムを
on this algorithm and make
改善する事が出来る。
it quite a bit more computationally efficient.
それでもっとずっと計算量的に効率的になる。
But, hopefully this gives you
でもこれで、別々の映画から、
a sense of how you
パラメータとフィーチャーを
can formulate a
同時に学習する、という問題を
problem where you can simultaneously
どう定式化するかが
learn the parameters and simultaneously learn the features from the different movies.
なんとなく分かったんじゃないかな。
And for this problem, for the
そしてこの問題に関して言うと、
recommender system problem, this is
リコメンダーシステムの問題に関して言うと、
possible only because each user
これが可能なのは、各ユーザーが
rates multiple movies and hopefully
複数の映画をレーティングしていて、
each movie is rated
さらに出来たら全ての映画が
by multiple users. And so
複数のユーザーにレーティングされてて初めて可能となる。
you can do this back and
つまり、この行ったり来たりして
forth process to estimate theta
シータとxを推計する手順が使用出来る。
and x. So to
ではまとめよう。
summarize, in this video we've
このビデオでは、
seen an initial collaborative filtering algorithm.
最初の協調的フィルタリングのアルゴリズムを見てきた。
The term collaborative filtering refers
協調的フィルタリングという用語は
to the observation that when
たくさんのユーザーに対して
you run this algorithm with a
このアルゴリズムを実行した時を観察すると、
large set of users, what all
全てのユーザーが
of these users are effectively doing are sort of
事実上、ある種の協調
collaboratively--or collaborating to
--またはコラボレーション-- をして、
get better movie ratings for
皆にとってより良い映画のレーティングを得ている事が
everyone because with every
観察される事による。何故なら各ユーザーが
user rating some subset with the movies,
映画のサブセットをレーティングする、という行動でもって
every user is helping the
アルゴリズムがちょっとだけ改善されたフィーチャーを得るのを
algorithm a little bit to learn better features,
各ユーザーが助けているからだ。
and then by helping--
そして助ける事で --
by rating a few movies myself, I will be helping
2, 3の映画を自分でレーティングする事で、
the system learn better features and
私はシステムがより良いフィーチャーを学習するのを助けている事になり、
then these features can be used
そしてこれらのフィーチャーを
by the system to make better
システムがその他全員に対して
movie predictions for everyone else.
映画のよりよい予測を行う為に使う事が出来る。
And so there is a sense of
つまりある種の協調作業が
collaboration where every user is
ある訳だ：各ユーザーが、
helping the system learn better features
公共の利益の為に、システムがより良いフィーチャーを
for the common good. This
学習するのを手助けする。
is this collaborative filtering.
これが協調的フィルタリングだ。
And, in the next video what we
そして次のビデオでやる事は、
going to do is take the ideas that
ここまでやってきたアイデアを
have worked out, and try to
用いて、より良いアルゴリズムの
develop a better an even
構築を試みる。
better algorithm, a slightly better
協調フィルタリングにとって
technique for collaborative filtering.
もうちょっとだけ良い方法を。